[poignant music playing]
Inako.
- Aah!
- [Naeko] Give it a sniff.
[gasps]
[sniffing] Aah!
Smells the same as last year!
I love it! Like warm tart apples,
but it's even sweeter this year!
Very impressive.
You're my little master brewer,
aren't you?
Mmm! I wanna be just like you!
[Naeko] Is that so?
Well, then, you need to pray to the gods.
[gasps] The gods?
[chuckles]
In order for the sake to be truly good,
we must pray to the gods
to dwell within it.
Only then will it be the kind of sake
that can make your heart shine.
Faith is essential to brewing.
We work hard,
put everything we have into the blends,
and then we pray and trust the gods.
That's the secret to making good sake.
Right!
- [Naeko coughing]
- [gasps]
Mother, are you okay?
- [Naeko sighs softly] I'm fine.
- [gasps happily]
- [Naeko] Now let's put our hands together.
- [sighs happily]
[Noriko] Are you all right?
It's so dark in here.
[Inako] I was looking for
Mother's sake brewing records.
- Do you know where they are?
- Uh… Oh.
Well, let's see if we can find them.
[Inako] They don't look
like they're in here.
Inako, do you…
want to be a master brewer?
[Inako] Mmm.
I have faith in you.
[gasps and chuckles]
- What's going on here?
- [gasps]
- I was looking for Mother's notes and--
- [Jinemon growls]
These notes won't do you any good!
[gasps]
[Jinemon] None of this will do you good
once you're married into the Mizoe family.
[Noriko] Father!
[sighs]
That girl.
Mm-hm.
Naeko, if you were here,
you'd know what to do.
[theme song in Japanese playing]
SPARKS OF TOMORROW
EPISODE 4: THE STEADFAST GIRL
We'll make this century
the Age of Electricity.
[Yosuke] This… is electricity?
This was Seiroku's dream?
And now… this dream belongs to me!
[cackles]
[Yosuke] I hate him!
That little brat!
[panting angrily]
I looked through the whole book.
It was nothing but scribbles.
How was he able
to build the Full Moon? [gasps]
Oh, that's it!
The catalog he showed me
must have been a decoy.
Which means that little brat
has got the real one
stashed away somewhere…
Hah! Bring me a change of clothes.
We're leaving at once!
[gentle music playing]
[woman] Two hiyashiame, please.
Coming up.
- [man 2] Here you go!
- [man 1] Enjoy!
- [Kate] Ah!
- Cold and delicious.
Everyone's talking about
this steam-cooled hiyashiame.
Good thing we passed by the food stalls.
[Suzu] And the surugaya yokan is
delicious too.
[whimsical music playing]
[Kihachi] He took the book with him to war
so he could write all this?
I guess I'll be spending the rest
of my life trying to create all of these.
If I do, the Age of Electricity will be…
- [shrieks]
- Hey, Kihachi!
- [whimpers]
- I thought you might celebrate with us!
M-maybe later.
It would be an affront to the food gods
to let such a wonderful drink go to waste.
It's sweet, cold, and delicious.
[Kihachi] It's good.
- [crash]
- [both gasp]
Hey, Sparky!
- Tell me where the real catalog is!
- Mr. Mizoe?
- Why's the white-haired freak here?
- [growls]
- Where did you hide it?
- [Kihachi] What?
[snarls] Search everywhere!
- Sir.
- [Kihachi yelps] Hey!
Do what you must!
- [yelps]
- [gasps] Mr. Mizoe!
- What the… [shrieks]
- [Izo] Mr. Mizoe!
[Yosuke] Release me at once!
[grunts]
[both] You're not welcome here!
Do you know who I am?
Wait, Mr. Mizoe.
These two appear to be ex-military.
I won't be able to take them on my own.
[snarls]
- [Yosuke] Damn you!
- [Kihachi] What's with that guy?
- [boy] Mommy!
- [man 1] Slow down!
[man 2] Oh, no, is he okay?
- Oh, my…
- Hey!
Hey, are you all right?
- [gasps] It's him!
- [woman] Huh?
[trembling]
[Inako] He's the young proprietor
at Nishikiya!
[Yosuke] It was you, wasn't it?
You hired those bodyguards!
I was their commander in the war.
The two mentioned
they were in need of work.
I gave them an introduction.
Don't play dumb, Kuga.
Why are you getting in my way?
Yosuke, you saw the Full Moon
with your own eyes.
[gasps]
I think for now,
you should wait and let things play out.
[growls]
[scoffs]
Forget it!
[cat meows]
[man whimpering] Banto!
The young master's been hurt!
- Wow, it's pretty dark in here.
- [both] Huh?
[Kihachi] Are they going out of business
or something?
[Inako] Kihachi! How could you say that?
Nishikiya is a traditional
NIshijin weaving shop.
[Banto panting]
Young master!
Thank you for your help.
I apologize if this ordeal
caused you any trouble.
It's fine, but may I ask
what happened, sir?
On the way over here…
Mommy.
…that's all he would say.
Indeed, it is a delicate matter.
The proprietress of this shop has
shut herself in her room as of late.
Did something happen?
[Banto] Sadly, yes. While she was away
dealing with business matters,
her husband,
the store's proprietor, collapsed.
- He passed before she could return.
- [somber music playing]
[Kihachi] It's not like
his passing was her fault.
[Banto] Even so, a melancholy has
fallen over her ever since.
- [crying]
- Little Bug?
It's because she wasn't able
to be with him when he passed.
- [crying] I'm sorry, Mommy…
- Uh…
- I know exactly how she feels!
Uh…
[sighs]
- [crashing]
- [yelps]
Sir, you can't do this!
- [Yosuke] Nishikiya!
- [all coughing]
I think it's about time you lay off
your pathetically outdated craftsmen,
and replace them with our steam looms.
That way,
you can actually repay your debt,
and I won't have to close down
your pitiful little shop.
To be frank, I do not have time
to deal with such trivial matters!
[Banto] Uh…
- I beg of you, Mr. Mizoe…
- [Yosuke scoffs]
[Yosuke and Kihachi]
What is he doing here?
Where is the real catalog?
You and I both know you're not
talented enough to build the Full Moon
without his schematics!
[Inako] Stop being so rude!
- Huh?
- [Yosuke] Darling girl.
It's time for you to start behaving
like a proper Mizoe wife, don't you think?
Gah! Kihachi is the most
talented person I've ever met!
His inventions are incredible!
It's thanks to him I was able to see
my mother in Paradise one last time!
What?
- Truly?
- [yelps]
Oh, If you were able to do that
for the proprietress,
if only she could actually speak
with her beloved husband one more time,
oh, I'm sure she'd be cured!
Yes, please, sir.
With her back, we wouldn't need
those steam-powered looms!
- Right, young master?
- Dada!
[man 1] Please, allow her
to see her husband one more time!
[man 2] Yes, we're begging you!
- [man 3] Help her.
- [boy] Mommy!
[Kihachi wails]
[Yosuke] He showed her the dead?
It looks like I was right all along.
That kind of advanced electricity…
If Sparky can do all that…
Wait! [gasps]
- [crashing]
- [Yosuke gasps]
- [sighs] I want him under surveillance.
- Sir.
[Inako] A bath?
Yep. Invention nine.
The Electric Hot Springs.
Electricity stimulates
the healing properties.
- Incredible!
- Yeah!
I can't help her talk to the dead.
But one bath in this,
and she'll definitely feel better.
It's like a dream!
- [crackling]
- Kihachi?
- [Kihachi gurgling]
- [gasps]
[Kihachi groaning]
Everything tingles.
I'm sorry, Kihachi.
I shouldn't have pulled you into this.
I think it might be three
instead of eight.
- [Kihachi] Here, let me see.
- [Yajiro] Okay.
I think it says…
It's no use. Damn.
The ink is all smudged. I can't read it.
Huh?
So we can't do the Electric Hot Spring?
Do you really wanna
put an old lady in this thing?
But without it, the proprietress is
never going to get any better.
I mean, I guess we have more options…
Hey, why are you
so invested in this, anyway?
Because I know how it feels
to lose someone so important.
- Kihachi.
- Huh?
Uh… [groans softly]
Uh… are you talking
about your mom right now?
[gasps]
[men chanting]
[Inako] My mother…
[chanting continues]
[Inako] When it came to making sake,
she was very strict.
But at home, she was kind.
She always had a hug waiting
for me and my sister.
[gasps]
[Inako] The sake my mother made
was always in demand.
That kept my father busy with deliveries.
[chanting continues]
[Inako] The brewery was
a much livelier place back then.
But then, my mother got sick
from breathing in all the soot.
And that winter…
I think about her every day.
There is so much
I still wanted to ask her.
About making sake,
or about the best places
to go on a trip together.
[sighs] There's so much
I wish I could say to her.
That's why I want
the proprietress to get better.
So that she and her son can talk
and continue
to experience their lives together!
Little Bug…
You were the one who figured out
how to create the Electric Full Moon,
so I know you can find a way
to let her speak with her husband again!
You can do anything, Kihachi!
I know you can!
[Kihachi] Uh…
THE 20TH CENTURY ELECTRICAL CATALOG
Speaking to the dead is impossible.
I've told you that many times now.
[gasps]
- [Kihachi] But you're right.
- Huh?
I can't just walk away from this either.
So we have to find a way to help her.
You mean it?
[Kihachi] Mmm.
[Kihachi] I'll arrange
for the proprietress
to speak with her husband one last time.
You said yesterday
that you couldn't do it!
- [Kihachi] I can't.
- [wails]
- But I can!
- Wait, what? You can?
[Suzu] How do you plan to do it?
Huh? You really want to know?
- Yes! Mm-hm.
- [Inako laughs]
The Electrical Catalog shows that you can
convert electricity into vibrations.
- Used to talk to someone far away.
- Right!
- The proprietor pretends to be his father…
- We can do it!
[girls whispering and giggling]
Want to get food on the way home?
I could go for something grilled.
[Inako] Sorry, I have to get to Nishikiya.
- [Kate] Huh?
- [Suzu] Hm.
[woman] Namu Amida Butsu.
Namu Amida Butsu. Namu Amida Butsu.
- Madam, please listen to me.
- Namu Amida Butsu.
Please listen to what I have to say!
Namu Amida Butsu. Namu Amida Butsu.
[groans]
Damn it!
How am I supposed to convert
sound vibrations into electricity?
How do I use the vibrations
to make it switch…
[wistful music playing]
[Inako] Madam, please listen to me!
[proprietress] You must
stop this behavior.
[soft hissing]
Ahh!
It's still not transmitting my voice.
[sighs] This won't work.
Please, child,
just leave me to my prayers.
My apologies, madam.
[gasps]
Uh… Huh?
[Kihachi's voice] Huh?
[gasps]
Carbon changes the electrical resistance…
Okay. I think I know
how to make this work!
Please come out of your room.
Madam. Come out.
I'm begging you.
[sighs]
- [Yajiro] Is everything ready?
- Yeah.
I guess all that's left now
is for the little bug
to bring the proprietress here.
[proprietress] You're back again?
I wish to be left alone
to grieve my loss in peace.
Madam, everyone is waiting
for you to come out.
Why do they waste their time
worrying about me?
For that matter, why do you?
Because… well, I just…
I don't want you to have any regrets!
[gasps]
I feel regret every day of my life!
I… I lost my own mother three years ago.
[gasps]
[Inako] There were still so many things
I wanted to ask her.
But I was just a child then.
I wasn't capable
of understanding what had happened.
And by the time
I finally understood, well,
it was too late.
Please, madam! Come out.
Your son misses you.
He wants to talk to you.
Banto and all the others do as well.
I don't want you or your son
to regret leaving anything unsaid,
so please come out,
even if for a little while.
Please, madam!
- [gasps]
- Perhaps you're right, young one.
Oh, madam!
I do not wish for any more regrets.
- [Inako] Thank you so much!
- [gasps]
[chuckle] I see that
the tenacity of youth still exists.
Uh… please forgive me!
Silly girl. It's thanks to you
I am able to leave this room.
[Inako] I'm so glad, because…
we're going to speak with your husband.
[gasps]
What did you say?
Madam, there is a machine
we'd like for you to see.
- Are you saying what I think you are?
- Yes!
You'll be able to speak with your husband!
[gasps] Is this real?
Such a machine exists?
- Of course! It does, madam!
- [gasps]
Yes! Yes!
- Let's go right away!
- Um…
- [yelps]
- Are you all right?
I've been locked in my room so long,
my muscles have fatigued.
- Don't worry, I'll help you downstairs.
- [proprietress groaning]
[breathing heavily]
- [Inako] Please, madam, go slow!
- Aah! Aah!
- [Inako shrieks] Slow down!
- [Inako yelps]
- [both groan]
- Oh! Ow! My leg! It's cramping!
- [Inako gasping]
- Inako!
- [both gasping]
Almost there…
[both panting]
[both groaning]
- [panting]
- Please, have a seat, ma'am.
[Inako moans]
[proprietress sighs shakily]
[soft hissing]
- [groans]
- [Kate chuckles]
[gasps]
Place your ear here.
Then, when you're ready, speak into this.
Mmm.
[trembles]
[low humming]
[male voice] Chiyo?
- [static buzzing]
- [gasps shakily]
Is that you?
[gasps]
[gasps and sobs]
You left us all so suddenly, I…
I didn't…
I didn't know what else to do.
We said we'd make the best shop in Kyoto.
So I worked. I worked so hard.
- I know.
- [Chiyo sobs]
I can't do this by myself. [sobbing]
I'm so tired.
[sniffles] And I don't know
when it happened,
but the business has gone downhill.
[Chiyo crying] I'm sorry.
[machine ticking and squeaking]
[shudders]
You… you don't have to push yourself.
[inhales]
The shop isn't the same
when you're not around.
Everyone is sad.
[high-pitched ringing]
[muffled sounds echoing]
[voices overlapping]
[poignant music playing]
[boy] I'm here. I want to see her.
[Kihachi sighs]
[Inako gasps]
[Chiyo] My love, I…
I… I promise you, I won't give up.
This old shop is filled
with so many precious memories.
Thank you.
[sobs] I should thank you, my love.
Oh, sir! [wailing]
[gasps]
[Chiyo] Hmm.
- My goodness.
- [gasps]
- [Chiyo] Look at the state of this place.
- [both chuckle]
[Chiyo] I suppose nothing
gets done without me.
[birdsong]
Mmm. Akira? Akira, come here.
- [all gasp]
- Mother!
Why are you all just standing there?
- Let's open the store.
- [all] Yes, ma'am!
[all laughing]
- Thank you so much, Inako.
- [gasps happily]
[Chiyo] All right, let's get to work!
[gasps] Did you see that?
You did it! It's like a dream, to be able
to talk to someone who's passed away!
- What?
- Can I…
- Can I talk to my mother next?
- Uh, no, that's impossible.
Huh? What do you mean, impossible?
- The proprietress was talking to her son.
- Huh?
[Kihachi] Electric Telepathy.
You can talk to people from far away!
What? So you didn't really summon
the spirit of her husband?
You can't be serious.
[shrieks]
- [Kihachi] Didn't I already explain this?
- [grunting]
Huh?
Still…
you brought the madam
a lot of joy and closure.
That was a really nice thing
you did for her.
Thank you, Kihachi!
[Kihachi] It's no big deal.
- What's important is Electric Telepathy.
- [Inako] Oh, okay…
[Kihachi] And carbon! Yeah, the carbon.
[bubbling fiercely]
[Izo] Mr. Mizoe.
I have a surveillance report for you.
The spirit of Nishikiya's
deceased proprietor appeared,
and they communicated for a few minutes
on a device similar to a phonograph.
[whirring]
[Yosuke] I have no doubt
that little brat is hiding
the real catalog from me.
It's happened again.
Your brother has stolen your ideas
and made them into reality.
[bell dings]
[gasps]
[elevator clicks]
[elevator clanking]
[Yosuke] Huh.
We both know you and I are the only ones
who should know
of the catalog's true secrets.
Isn't that right?
["Soarin'" by Ginger Root playing]
Seiroku.
I swear this to you,
when I get my hands on the real catalog,
our dreams will come true.
♪ Looking up and within ♪
♪ To try and move forward ♪
♪ Get back what you gave in ♪
♪ To drag yourself in ♪
[lyrics in Japanese]
♪ Oh, I'll be waitin' ♪
♪ Look at how far we've come ♪
♪All together ♪
♪ Soarin' ♪
[lyrics in Japanese]
♪ When I'm with you ♪
♪ Somethin' tells me I'm gonna be alone ♪